Good morning, today is ראש חודש אב, Rosh Chodesh Av, we are
on נ"ד עמוד א', Nun Dalet Amud Aleph, we'll start towards the
top just to set again the background for what comes up on
the rest of the דף, daf, and I am Dan Margulies, I
am filling in for Rabbi Linzer as he continues to be on
vacation, he should return to us soon.
Will he be here for שבת Shabbat or is he?
I think I'm here for שבת Shabbat and he will not be
here for...
but he will not be here for שבת. Shabbat. Okay.
The original agreement did not include me filling in for him on
Sunday, but I don't know whether he will be back on Sunday
or not. Again, I don't know his travel arrangements, so I'll probably
try to get in touch with him today and find out the
details. Okay. So, the משנה mishnah says: הנודר מן הירק מותר בדלועים.
Hanoder min hayerek mutar badiluim. If a person takes a נדר neder
not to get a benefit from vegetables, the person is permitted to
eat pumpkin. So the question is why would pumpkin not be included
in ירק? yerek? What is the point of something being ירק? yerek?
If we look in the right at beginning of the ר"ן, Ran,
the ר"ן Ran says: הנודר מן הירק מותר בדלועים דלא הוי ירק
אלא פרי. Hanoder min hayerek mutar badiluim dela havei yerek ela pri.
It's not a vegetable, it is a fruit. This is one of
my favorite lines.
Knowledge is knowing that a tomato is a fruit, wisdom is not
putting it in fruit salad. So this pumpkin is a fruit. ואיכא
דמפרשי, ve'ika demifarshei, there are those who would explain: דסתם ירק נאכל
כמות שהוא חי. desatam yerek ne'echal kemoto shehu chai. When you say
ירק, yerek, you mean something that is edible while raw.
דלועים אינן כן. diluim einan kein. So there are two different possibilities.
Number one, דלועים, diluim, pumpkin, is not a vegetable, is not perhaps
it is not a green leafy vegetable. The word ירק yerek is
green, so it's something green. It is a פרי, pri, fruit, it
grows on a vine, something like that. Or alternatively because it's not
edible raw. So the question of something being edible raw has a
lot of implications for a variety of הלכות. halachot. Number one is
on שבת. Shabbat. There is at least a discussion in the ראשונים
Rishonim about foods that are edible raw. Does it really count as
cooking on שבת Shabbat if you cook them? And the opinion that's
followed להלכה la'halacha is yes. However, תוספות Tosafot and the מרדכי Mordechai
bring an example of different kinds of baked apples and things like
that that perhaps the argument was trying to be made that the
apples are still edible but and so they never turn from something
inedible to something edible. However, they do undergo a qualitative change in
being cooked. They become a baked apple, it becomes soft and mushy
and has a different flavor.
And other examples are...
but we still say it's a problem.
Right, exactly. But we end up פסקן-ing pasken להלכה la'halacha is that
it is a problem. It's that to cook a food which is
edible raw, you would still be חייב chayav on שבת. Shabbat. For
example, I mean the best example is water. To boil up a
pot of water. Water is edible while cold, it's also edible while
hot. You didn't functionally change the water anyway, you just heated it.
So there you go.
The interesting question is what about food that's partially cooked? Food that's
partially cooked is a big מחלוקת machloket if taking something which is
already edible, cooked edible, like a rare cooked steak and cooking it
further.
It seems that the רשב"א Rashba would say that such cooking is
not cooking anymore. Once something is edible, once something has been cooked
enough to be edible, then it's cooked להלכה la'halacha and you don't
have to worry about it anymore. And the רשב"א Rashba would say
it's you're not חייב chayav at least מדאורייתא mide'oraita for cooking a
rare steak. A rare steak is already sitting on your plate and
you put it back on the fire, that would not be חייב
chayav according to the רשב"א. Rashba. The רמב"ם Rambam disagrees. The רמב"ם
Rambam says until something is fully cooked, any further cooking would continue
to cook it to the point that it improves in such a
way that that improvement up until being fully cooked would still be
the דאורייתא מלאכה בישול. de'oraita melacha bishul. And the שלטי גבורים Shiltei
Gibborim if I remember correctly, the שלטי גבורים Shiltei Gibborim fascinatingly enough
said even something which is fully cooked, but if continuing to cook
it will improve it, that also counts as the מלאכה דאורייתא: melacha
de'oraita: מצטמק ויפה לו. mitztamek veyafeh lo. עד שנצטמק... ad shenitztamek... ורע
לו. vera lo. Exactly. Until it dries out and gets worse, but
if further cooking would improve the food, then the fact that you're
further cooking it and it is improving is the מלאכה melacha as
well. Other places where נאכל כמות שהוא חי ne'echal kemoto shehu chai
is important is בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum, touched on before. בישול עכו"ם
bishul akum that a food which is edible raw, בישול עכו"ם bishul
akum would not apply because if it's edible raw then the non-Jew's
involvement in its preparation is irrelevant. You could eat it raw. So
carrots you can eat raw, so therefore cooked carrots it doesn't matter.
And the application to as we discussed sushi, how sushi people's eating
tastes have changed, fish is now something considered edible while raw.
Of course the rice is as
well.
And it is always baked.
Well, but now Jewish people like sushi, you know, we're whatever 30
years behind the times. Okay. So, the משנה mishnah says: הנודר מן
הירק מותר בדלועים. hanoder min hayerek mutar badiluim. But go back to
the fruit thing though.
You would think that like if someone says okay now I can't
have an apple, right? When the ר"ן Ran is saying fruit, he
doesn't mean that.
Meaning, the ר"ן Ran says there are two things, there's fruits and
there's vegetables and if I say I'm נודר מן הירק, noder min
hayerek,
the ר"ן Ran is telling me דלועים, diluim, pumpkin, falls into the
fruits category not into the...
Okay so the משנה Mishnah said אני נדור מן
הירק מותר בדלועים ורבי עקיבא.
ani nador min hayerek mutar
bediluim v'Rabbi Akiva. But what about the fruit thing though?
You would think that if someone says okay now you can't have
an apple, right?
When the ר"ן Ran is saying fruit, he doesn't mean that. Meaning
the ר"ן Ran says there are two things: there's fruit and there's
vegetables and if I say אני נדור מן הירק ani nador min
hayerek the ר"ן Ran is telling me דלועים diluim pumpkin falls into
the fruit category, not into the vegetable. Because it's not הירק. hayerek.
Oh because the דלועים diluim is a פרי. pri. It is a
פרי. pri. Okay good. So then he could have said anything then.
So he could have said he should have said then מותר בפירות,
mutar bepayrot, right? But I mean no because דלועים diluim is a
case of something that we thought might be vegetable and the משנה
Mishnah is coming to tell me no it's not a vegetable it's
a fruit. Okay. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אוסר. oser. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva disagrees with the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and says that you
would not be allowed to eat דלועים. diluim. אמרו לו לרבי עקיבא
והלא אומר אדם לשלוחו קח לי ירק ואומר לא
מצאתי אלא דלועין.
Amru lo l'Rabbi Akiva vehalo omer adam lishlucho kach li yerek veomer
lo matzati ela diluin.
Isn't it true that if a person sends someone to go to
the grocery store for and the שליח shaliach comes back and says
they didn't have any vegetables but they did have pumpkins?
Okay. So isn't that proof say the חכמים Chachamim that it is
a vegetable? Sorry, that that it is not a vegetable, meaning that
I wanted vegetables and the שליח shaliach comes back and says they
didn't have vegetables, they had pumpkins. He comes back empty-handed. However רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva will respond והוא אומר אמר להן. vehu omer amar
lahen. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says כן הדבר, ken hadavar, that's true, however I interpret it differently
as we're going to see in the גמרא. Gemara. או שמא אומר
הוא לא מצאתי אלא קטנית אלא שהדלועים בכלל ירק והקטנית אינו בכלל
ירק. O shema omer hu lo matzati ela kitnit ela shehadiluim bichlal
yerek vehakitnit eino bichlal yerek.
Because a person who says please go get me some vegetables, the
person comes back from the store and says they didn't have any
vegetables but they did have beans. No one would say that because
beans are too far removed from vegetables. Beans are I never would
have even thought about beans. So the fact that you're telling me
no one would say beans, the fact that you're telling me they
do have pumpkin means that pumpkin is close enough to vegetables to
be included in the נדר neder because the need to specify, the
need to say they did not have vegetables but they did have
pumpkins becomes a statement pumpkin is a vegetable and it's I know
that it was not the vegetable that you wanted.
So the מחלוקת machlokes between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and חכמים Chachamim
sounds to be like a debate about when a person feels the
need to specify they didn't have X but
they did have Y, then is that inclusive or exclusive? Is the
need to say specify saying this is part of the category you're
asking about or it is outside the category?
It's like saying a tomato is a fruit.
It's like saying tomato's a fruit.
So no קטנית? kitnit?
So no קטנית kitnit or
vegetable?
Or pumpkin?
Okay, so number one, so what about gourds? What are you saying?
Oh they're fruits. Pumpkins are fruit.
Well that's the first line in the ר"ן Ran we just saw.
Yeah. So the question about קטנית kitnit is exactly the next line
in the משנה: Mishnah: ואסור בפול המצרי לח ומותר ביבש. vaasur beful
hamitzri lach umutar beyavesh. That beans sometimes are considered vegetables and sometimes
not. Even קטניות, kitniyot, meaning even according to רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
proof that even beans you would say are not vegetables? No, sometimes
beans really are vegetables. So maybe there's a way to read that
actually as part of what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying or
maybe that's a סתם משנה,
stam Mishnah, a gloss on רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva by strengthening it.
Right.
This line supports רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position because even פול המצרי
ful hamitzri which is a bean, a קטנית, kitnit, nonetheless when it
is fresh, when it is green beans, green beans we know are
a vegetable, but beans, dry beans are beans. So at some point
even the plant which is a vegetable, there's some need to specify
about whether the beans are in fact in the vegetable category or
not. Okay, says the גמרא: Gemara: תנן המודר מן הירק והוא מן
הירק נדר. tenan hamudar min hayerek vehu min hayerek nadar. But so
didn't you just say oh I'm taking a נדר neder from vegetables?
So meaning that what? Meaning there's no specificity in the נדר, neder,
there's no precision in the נדר. neder. It sounds like this נדר
neder would be more inclusive because you said ירק yerek and even
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should agree that the word ירק yerek is
inclusive enough to include דלועים diluim even though he does not think
that דלועים diluim should be considered ירקות yerakot in general. So how
is it? Meaning what לשון lashon of the נדר neder did you
actually use? Because it doesn't seem to fit. ירק yerek sounds too
inclusive to really allow that. אמר עולא באומר ירקי קדרה עלי. Amar
Ulla beomer yarkei kedeirah alai. No, so עולא Ulla says the משנה
Mishnah must be talking about a case where he was more specific
and the person said ירקי קדרה עלי, yarkei kedeirah alai, vegetables for
the pot are forbidden to me. ודלמא ירק הנאכל בקדרה קאמר? Vedilma
yerek hane'echal bekedeirah ka'amar?
Or באומר ירק המתבשל בקדרה עלי? beomer yerek hamitbashel bekedeirah alai? Or
so and in response to עולא Ulla the גמרא Gemara suggests what
do you mean? Perhaps he said other formulations which even though they
sound more specific are actually relatively inclusive, either vegetables that are eaten
in a pot or vegetables which are cooked in a pot. And
so עולא Ulla is saying the לשון lashon must have been more
inclusive to include to try to even suggest including דלועים diluim and
the response is well what do you mean? Any kind of these
any of these formulations would be inclusive to the point where עולא's
Ulla position doesn't matter very much.
Now the רשב״א Rashba here suggests that this precision question about are
pumpkins categorized as vegetables or not, or similar examples, the רשב״א Rashba
extends it based on the ירושלמי Yerushalmi to other areas of הלכה
Halacha as well. This isn't just something that applies to נדרים, Nedarim,
this question, but it also would apply in commerce and in the
הלכות Halachot of הפקר. Hefker. If a person says all of my
vegetables are הפקר, Hefker, well, did he mean to include the pumpkins
or not? So that's a very good question. So that's what the
רשב״א Rashba is getting at here, that this is really a much
more broad question about what is included when you say the word
vegetable.
So I have a question.
Is the רשב״א Rashba on the page in the ר״ן Ran or
so?
Or are you the רשב״א Rashba from outside?
The רשב״א Rashba from outside. From outside. So at what point, you
know, some point can it change? Like let's say you say okay
vegetables are אסור Assur and then you make let's
let's take zucchini's a vegetable, okay? Okay. And then someone makes a
zucchini bread, right?
Is it vegetable or
is it bread, you know?
That's a very good question. You know the prepared question is if
this ingredient was prepared that was what we had somewhat yesterday when
we had about the מקפה Mikpeh and the שום Shum that the
garlic is an ingredient in this porridge and different things.
I don't have a good answer for that but again it depends
as to what extent is the if you say zucchini bread it
sounds like based on what we were saying about the Milky Way
and other examples like that where it has the שם Shem it
has the name of what it was included now in it. You
say it's חומץ Chometz of סתווניות, Stavanoyot, right? Or it's the
שמן שומשומין. Shemen Shumshumin. So all of those that still carry the
name. So if you would say zucchini bread probably would still be
considered zucchini but maybe you know that's יוצא מהם Yotzei meihem kind
of a question. Okay. So
we say here במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamipalgi? What are the רבנן Rabbanan
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva really disagreeing about? רבנן סברי כל מילתא
דצריך שליחא לאמלוכי עליה לאו מיניה הוא. Rabbanan savri kol milta d'tzarich
shlicha l'amlokei alei lav minei hu. The רבנן Rabbanan say anything which
a שליח Shaliach comes back to report and to clarify, to ask
a question from the משלח Meshaleach about or to report back to
him, that means it is not part of that species. That's what
we were saying. Meaning the רבנן Rabbanan say if the שליח Shaliach
comes back and says I did not find vegetables but I did
find pumpkins, that means it is not that pumpkin is not a
vegetable because I said they did not have vegetables but they did
have pumpkins. However, ורבי עקיבא סבר כל מילתא דממלוך שליח עליה מיניה
הוא. V'Rabbi Akiva savar kol milta d'mimloch shlicha alei minei hu. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says anything a שליח Shaliach comes back to specify,
he's saying the only vegetable they had was pumpkin. Not they did
not have vegetables but they did have pumpkins, but the only vegetable
they had was pumpkin. And therefore coming to clarify back to the
משלח, Meshaleach, hey do you want me to go get pumpkin or
not because they have pumpkin even though they don't have any other
vegetable, that becomes a question of מיניה הוא. Minei hu. It is
included in that category.
Okay.
אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So אביי Abaye says so that's where we
got up to yesterday.
אמר אביי מודה רבי עקיבא לעניין מלקות שאינו לוקה. Amar Abaye modeh
Rabbi Akiva l'inyan malkot she'eino lokeh. אביי Abaye says no even רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees that מדאורייתא Mid'oraita or in order to make
you חייב Chayav in lashes for violating your נדר, Neder, if I
took a נדר Neder I will not eat you know vegetables are
אסור Assur to me to my mouth and then I eat a
piece of pumpkin,
so even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva will agree that I don't get
מלקות Malkos for that. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's אסור, Assur,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I'm not allowed to eat the pumpkin
but he won't say I get lashes for it. He won't say
that I really violated בל יחל. Bal yachal. Yes.
Is that because because
we say ספק נדרים לחומרא Safek nedarim l'chumra but still it does
not include the punishment?
Is it because this statement here אביי Abaye is essentially saying רבי
עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva statement is a statement of ספק לחומרא? Safek l'chumra?
And therefore maybe you would be מיקל Meikel with the עונש? Onesh?
In some sense, right. We can't say עונשין מן הדין Onshin min
hadin and things like that so at least if you have some
leg to stand on maybe we can't punish you but you still
violated the איסור Issur because of the fact that this is still
some kind of a gray area. There's room to say that it
is prohibited because we say ספק נדרים להחמיר Safek nedarim l'hachmir that
we treat נדרים Nedarim stringently but that we at the same time
would not go so far to bring the punishment. There is some
discussion I think in the רמב״ם Rambam about how the רמב״ם Rambam
navigates this question that whether this is because of a sort of
a technical exemption about the rules of התראה Hatra-ah warning someone because
you have to be very specific when you warn someone that they're
breaking an עבירה Aveira that the witnesses have to say you know
you're about to violate X and they say this and then so
in that respect maybe it's some kind of a technical out. So
even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thinks yes it is included in מדאורייתא,
Mid'oraita, it is prohibited מדאורייתא Mid'oraita but there's a technical reason why
because of this ספק safek issue, because of this gray area about
whether it really is ירק yarak or not. If I said, "I
took a נדר neder against ירק," yarak, and then someone says, "You
know you're eating pumpkin, you're going to violate בל יחל," Bal Yachal,
well maybe they don't they can't actually say that because it's not
really included in the same way. Okay. תנן הכא. Tanan hacha. So
now we're going to discuss some of the הלכות halachot about שליחות
shlichut as they apply here because we're saying that the שליח, shaliach,
the שליח shaliach becomes now a room to talk about שליחות. shlichut.
And number one, most of the big סוגיות sugyot about שליחות shlichut
are in קידושין, Kiddushin, so they'll be coming up in a few
months.
Two of the important points to focus on: number one is the
שלוחו של אדם כמותו, shlucho shel adam k'moto, in some sense creating
a שליח shaliach means another person has your halachic power but also
stands in your stead to a certain point. There are different kinds
of שליח shaliach for different kinds of things. To what extent have
you created an independent person who can act of his own will
but is doing it for you? Or how much is the שליח
shaliach really an extension of the original person?
Actually before going into שליחות shlichut just one other
point, before going into שליחות shlichut one other point about this משנה
mishna about the question of ירק yarak and דלועים diluim about going
back and asking, so some of the אחרונים achronim based on this
משנה mishna wanted to think about what we call חמר מדינה. chamar
medina. חמר מדינה chamar medina is a certain kind of beverage that
the גמרא gemara mentions that you could say קידוש kiddush on, you
could say הבדלה havdala on, that this is חמר מדינה, chamar medina,
the local wine. That it's not wine. It may be שכר שעורים,
shechar se'orim, it may be beer, it may be something else, date
wine, who knows? It's something produced presumably with alcohol, but again the
אחרונים achronim get into it
that there is a drink which could be used as a stand-in
for wine because of its local significance. So the question is if
a person sends a person, "Please go and get me some wine
from the store," and the person comes back and says,
if someone comes back and says they didn't have wine but they
had beer, so that's basically the same as this. Is that saying,
"Ah, beer is included in wine" or it's separate from wine? Or
the other examples, רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein has a relatively
well-known תשובה teshuvah where he discusses this at length and he discusses
מי סודה, mei soda, seltzer water, whether seltzer water would be included
or not because really it's water but it's in some sense more
significant and people drink it. And רב משה Rav Moshe's criterion basically
boils down to: do you drink it when you're not thirsty? Do
you drink it just to drink it as an enjoyable experience or
are you drinking it only because you're thirsty? That's really how רב
משה Rav Moshe boils it down. Other פוסקים poskim disagree and they
base it on sort of is it something that you would give
to guests?
I never drink when I'm not thirsty.
So that's a very good question. You know some people and some
people don't, maybe may not ever drink something called חמר מדינה. chamar
medina. But something that's alcoholic beverages for example are often enjoyed socially.
You would give it
to a guest whether it's water or... right, and you would give
guests water, exactly.
So that doesn't really help.
So these are all different questions. There's a relatively well-known story about
רב חיים מבריסק Rav Chaim mi-Brisk that someone came to him and
asked, "Can I use milk for the four cups at the סדר?"
seder? And he said, "No," and he gives him a lot of
money out of his wallet to go and he sends him on
his way to do his יום טוב Yom Tov preparations. And his
wife says, "What do you mean? You פסקן paskin that you could
use milk for the four cups." So רב חיים Rav Chaim presumably
held that milk was considered חמר מדינה. chamar medina. And he says,
"No, but if he's asking whether he can have milk for the
four cups, it means he's not going to have any meat at
the סדר seder and he's not going to have any עונג יום
טוב, Oneg Yom Tov, he's not going to have a nice meal
at all, he's really scraping by." So he gave him enough money
to really have a nice יום טוב Yom Tov and that's a
very nice story about you know how much you have to read
בין השיטין bein hashitin just what the question is but getting into
what's really going with the person and the question they're asking.
It's a good thing that there were no vegetarians in Brisk.
Well at that time vegetarianism you know again wasn't so popular.
Okay.
One of the big issues here with שליחות shlichut is going to
be the question of שליח לדבר עבירה. shaliach lidvar aveirah. Sending a
שליח shaliach to do an עבירה aveirah for you.
Which we say אין שליח לדבר עבירה.
ein shaliach lidvar aveirah. There is no... you cannot send a שליח
shaliach to do an עבירה aveirah for you. There's three different ways
to understand what that means. We'll get to that in a second.
But there are three exceptions to אין שליח לדבר עבירה ein shaliach
lidvar aveirah where we do say there is שליח לדבר עבירה. shaliach
lidvar aveirah. One is by מעילה. me'ilah. So if I send my
שליח shaliach to go, "Here's my money of הקדש, hekdesh, please go
spend it at the grocery store," well that's he's violating it for
me. That's from a פסוק. pasuk. שליחות יד. shlichut yad. שליחות יד
shlichut yad is a שומר shomer is watching an object and decides
to use it for his own use. So also sending a שליח
shaliach to do that would also
work, it would go back. And the third is by ד ו-ה,
dalet v'hei, that slaughtering a stolen animal or selling it, just like
selling it involves another person, so too slaughtering it could even be
by שליח. shaliach. Okay. So the question is what does it mean
אין שליח... shaliach yes?
So I was once placed in a situation where I was instructed
to go buy
non-כשר... They said it's not a problem as long as I get
kosher food for any of the Jews who wanted kosher food because
it's not my עבירה. aveira.
It's an interesting point. The question becomes also about לפני עור, lifnei
iver, how much are you setting up a situation where other people
are going to be eating something not kosher? How much are there
questions about responsibility and ערבות arvut and different kinds of things? It's
a very interesting question and I'd love to hear more about, you
know, what that...
I actually had a different rabbi who פסק paskened
similarly for me on that. So that's good to hear, that it's
based at least based on this principle that look, you're... so then
getting into what it means אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein shaliach l'dvar
aveira, there is no שליח shaliach for to do a sin for
you. Does that mean that what you're trying to say is that
the person sending the שליח shaliach, is פטור? patur? The person who
sends the שליח, shaliach it doesn't go back to him. So that
the person doing the עבירה, aveira, so that maybe that's one thing,
is that saying okay fine, the person doing the עבירה aveira for
sure is חייב. chayav. But the person who sent the שליח shaliach
is פטור? patur? Why? Because the principle דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד דברי
מי שומעים. divrei harav v'divrei hatalmid divrei mi shomim. Why should he
listen to me? If he decides, if I tell someone, hey, you
go murder, you know, murder someone,
that's up to him. He knows that that's wrong, he knows it's
against the law, and he knows that it's morally wrong, etc. So
he shouldn't be doing that. Why should he listen to me? So
if he says, yeah, but I was just listening to what he
told me to do,
just taking orders, just taking
orders, it comes into the question in the military and things like
that, but the just taking orders argument to a certain extent דברי
הרב ודברי התלמיד דברי מי שומעים. divrei harav v'divrei hatalmid divrei mi
shomim. We say God's law takes precedence over trying to listen to
what someone's instructions are to you. So that's what would make the
משלח meshaleach פטור, patur, the person sending the שליח shaliach is not
counted as if he did the עבירה. aveira. On the flip side,
the other side is to say, to say that the שליח shaliach
should be חייב. chayav. Meaning, this is a person who did not
contemplate doing this, this is a person who did not formulate this
idea of his own. This is someone else's idea and it was
just asked to do it for him. So maybe to say that
the שליח shaliach is חייב chayav requires a proof in a certain
sense. And then the third point is that as we've seen in
other examples throughout this מסכת masechet and in other places as well,
that to be able to send a שליח shaliach is the same
criteria as being able to make a תנאי. tnai. Being able to
make some kind of a conditional statement is equivalent to being able
to send a שליח shaliach, because it demonstrates that you actually are
in control of the situation. If I can say this act is
on condition of X, that's because I'm in control of it. But
an עבירה, aveira, the God's law from the תורה Torah to violate
an עבירה aveira
is not up to me. I'm not in control of it. So
I can't make a תנאי tnai on an עבירה, aveira, so I
also can't make a שליח לדבר עבירה. shaliach l'dvar aveira. To do
a מצוה mitzvah for me maybe there is because doing a מצוה
mitzvah for someone and again that gets into there's a one of
the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid that gets quoted a lot, תוספות רי"ד
Tosafot Rid in קידושין Kiddushin in talking about שליח, shaliach שליח לדבר
מצוה, shaliach l'dvar mitzvah, sending a שליח shaliach to do a מצוה
mitzvah for you distinguishes between מצוה שבגופו, mitzvah she'begufu, a מצוה mitzvah
that you do with your body compared to other מצוות mitzvot because
a מצוה mitzvah that you do with your own body like wearing
תפילין tefillin or wearing תפילין tefillin is a good example, that's this
example, you can't have someone else put on תפילין tefillin for you
on their body for you because it's on their body. They're doing
the מצוה, mitzvah, it's not you. It's מצוה שבגופו. mitzvah she'begufu. So
no one else can do it for you. But other מצוות mitzvot
you could. So someone can light שבת Shabbat candles for you because
the מצוה mitzvah will be in the house, not on you and
things like that. And then also earlier in the מסכת masechet we
saw that by נזיר nazir you could make a נזירות, nezirot, you
could make a נדר neder on a תנאי tnai because someone else
can bring the קרבנות korbanot for you. And so the fact that
someone else can bring the קרבנות korbanot for you is a שליחות,
shelichut, is proof that you could make a נזירות על תנאי nezirot
al tnai as well. Okay.
So תנן התם, tnan hatam, השליח שעשה שליחותו, hashaliach she'asah shelichuto, a
שליח shaliach. who did the task that he was assigned to do,
בעל הבית מעל. baal habayit maal. Then the בעל הבית, baal habayit,
the owner, is
has violated the מעילה. meilah. מעילה meilah is using הקדש, hekdesh, using
temple property in an inappropriate way, stealing it or using it for
your own purposes. So this becomes a principle that מעילה meilah is
an exception for שליח לדבר עבירה shaliach l'dvar aveira because we're going
to see why soon. So השליח שעשה שליחותו, hashaliach she'asah shelichuto, if
I say Michael, please take this money and go buy me a
watermelon at the grocery store, and it turns out the money was
הקדש, hekdesh, so השליח שעשה שליחותו, hashaliach she'asah shelichuto, if he actually
buys me the watermelon that I asked for, then בעל הבית
מעל,
baal habayit
maal,
sorry, sorry, בעל הבית מעל. baal habayit maal. Then I've violated מעילה
meilah and he was just an extension of me, he was my
שליח. shaliach לא עשה שליחותו, lo asah shelichuto, but if instead of
buying me a watermelon he buys me cornflakes, but a pumpkin, or
perhaps a pumpkin, שליח מעל, shaliach maal, then it's the שליח shaliach
who is מעל maal because you broke your שליחות. shelichut. You decided
on your own. So this משנה mishna sounds like we should say
יש שליח לדבר עבירה yesh shaliach l'dvar aveira and that's why מעילה
meilah ends up getting determined to be an exception.
Doesn't it make a difference if the שליח shaliach knows
what
he's doing?
Money and go buy whatever and then it turns out it was
הקדש *hekdesh*, you know, but it was בשוגג *beshogeg* or it was
אונס *ones* in some situation, you know, there may be room to
get around it in different ways, but yeah, you still have to
watch out for that kind of thing.
Yeah, I mean nobody has הקדש *hekdesh* money lying around nowadays anyway.
Okay, so מאן תנא tanna *man tana*? So
stolen money becomes interesting question.
עבירה *aveira*. There are עבירות *aveirot* where he doesn't know.
So stolen money becomes a very interesting question of חולק עם הגנב
*cholek im aganav* and גונב מן הגנב *gonev min aganav*, you know,
being involved with a thief in some way, either stealing something from
a thief. He says, oh well, he was a thief so he
didn't own it anyway, I'm stealing it from him. Or, or
doing business deals with stolen property. There are a lot of סוגיות
*sugyot* about that and it becomes a big topic. It's very interesting.
צדקה *tzedakah* as well.
What's an example? And צדקה *tzedakah* money we have the question about
מעילה *meilah*. נדרים nedarim *nedarim* have a certain מעילה *meilah* and צדקה
*tzedakah* has a certain מעילה *meilah*. Okay, so we'll keep going. But
מאן תנא *man tana*? So how does this fit like? Who fits
this משנה mishnah *mishna*? אמר רב Rav חסדא מתניתין לא כרבי עקיבא
*amar Rav Chisda matnitin lo ke-Rabbi Akiva*. Our משנה mishnah *mishna*, meaning
the משנה mishnah *mishna* of מעילה *meilah*, does not seem to fit
like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva? *Rabbi Akiva*. דתנן כיצד אמר לו תן
בשר basar, לאורחין ונתן להם כבד *de-tanan keitzad amar lo ten basar
le-orchin ve-natan lahem kaved*. Because why? Because
if I have another משנה Mishnah *mishna*. The משנה Mishnah *mishna* says,
if I said to the house butler, please serve meat to the
guests, and he gives them liver. Okay.
So what? תן בשר basar לאורחין ונתן להם כבד תן כבד ונתן
להם בשר basar, השליח מעל *ten basar le-orchin ve-natan lahem kaved ten
kaved ve-natan lahem basar hashaliach ma'al*. Then the שליח shaliach. *shaliach* is
מעל *ma'al*. Now here מעל *ma'al* may not actually mean מעילה *meilah*.
Here it just means the שליח shaliach *shaliach* has violated the agreement
of the שליחות *shlichut*. But perhaps if the meat were in some
way הקדש *hekdesh* or something, then it would be מעילה *meilah*. But
it sounds really just like they're using the word מעל *ma'al* to
mean violated the agreement of the שליחות *shlichut*, meaning it's bad. It's
bad. I asked you to give meat and you gave liver. Well,
liver isn't meat and meat isn't liver. So then ah, so that
sounds like it doesn't seem to fit רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva*.
It doesn't mean he can't have a dairy though.
Because why? Because רבי Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
said if the שליח shaliach *shaliach* will go back and check, then
going, then
it is included. But here, okay,
if I would send you to the store and say please get
some meat and you come back and say oh, well they didn't
have meat but they did have liver. Well then
according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* then it would be included, but
here it sounds like it doesn't fit רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* because
it's not included. He said no, ואי רבי עקיבא הא אמר רבי
עקיבא כל מילתא דממלכא השליח מיניה *ve-i Rabbi Akiva ha amar Rabbi
Akiva kol milta de-mimlecha hashaliach minei*. No,
so רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* can respond, if you're going to say
it's not רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* can still
say no no no. I said the fact is when the שליח
shaliach *shaliach* actually has to go back and check. But here in
this example, the שליח *shaliach* didn't go back and check. The שליח
*shaliach* just did it on his own. So that's why. He didn't
check. If he had gone back and checked and said if he
would say hey, you know, what do you want me to do?
You have liver here, is the liver the meat that you want
or not? So that kind of a situation, that act of clarification
would indicate that liver and meat are in the same category. But
if there's no one asking the question, it's the need to specify,
it's the need to clarify that actually makes the point for רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. אמר רבי עקיבא כל מילתא דממלכא השליח מיניה *amar
Rabbi Akiva kol milta de-mimlecha hashaliach minei*. ממאן בעל הבית *mim'on ba'al
habayit*? So couldn't... so meaning... so the משנה *mishna* said מעל *ma'al*.
Someone was מעל *ma'al*. So we ask, well does that, can we
say השליח מעל *hashaliach ma'al*? Is it the שליח *shaliach* who was
מעל *ma'al*? And then we have this proof that it sounds like
even according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and certainly according to the
חכמים *chachamim* that that the שליח *shaliach* wouldn't fit with the שליח
*shaliach*. So we say בעל הבית מעל *ba'al habayit ma'al*. Right, so
למאן בעל הבית *lim'on ba'al habayit*. Right, so to make the בעל
הבית *ba'al habayit* חייב *chayav* and not the שליח *shaliach*. Meaning now
referencing back to our מעילה *meilah* question, which is that the בעל
הבית *ba'al habayit*, the one who sends the שליח *shaliach* should be
חייב *chayav* and not the שליח *shaliach*, because the fact is שליח
לא עשה שליחותו *shaliach lo asa shlichuto*. Okay, אמר אביי amar Abaye,
אפילו תימא רבי עקיבא *amar Abaye afilu tima Rabbi Akiva*. Even if
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says it's not... מודה רבי עקיבא דצריך
אימלוכא *modeh Rabbi Akiva de-tzarich imlucha*. So because רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
requires that you actually check, right? In the מפורש *meforesh* he says
השליח בעל הבית ואף על גב דסבר ליה דמיניהו דמילתא דצריך לאימלוכי
הכי איבעי ליה למימר שלח לבעל הבית רוצה אתה שאיתן להם כבד
*hashaliach ba'al habayit ve-af al gav de-savar lei de-mineihu de-milta de-tzarich le-imuchei
hachi ibayei leimeimar shalich le-ba'al habayit rotzeh ata she-eten lahem kaved* meaning
he's going to come back and ask, hey do you want me
to give them liver? So the act of asking is what serves
to clarify and that's what רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* was talking about.
But that's... but I mean something... it's more I would think if
it's askable, right?
Ah no, so that's the point.
No, but like let's say you say okay go get me fruit
and I said oh, well they didn't have fruit but I went
to Home Depot and they had wood, what do you want me
to do? Okay, so that's different. Right, you know what I mean?
Right. You know.
So but again, this is what אביי Abaye *Abaye* is saying. It's
not just enough that it is something that whether you would ask
or not, but it really is whether almost in the case he
did ask.
No, but like ask... Askable, meaning like it's something that you would,
right, that would be in the פרשה of ask, I would say.
But not just that. Meaning I think what אביי Abaye is actually
saying is that it really would be if you, if he does
come back and
asking and you have asked both.
For sure it has to be something that would be reasonable to
ask about. So איתמר שמעתא קמיה דרבא. itmar shmaita kmai d'Rava. This,
this סוגיא sugia was taught before רבא, Rava, meaning אביי Abaye was
teaching in front of רבא. Rava. אביי Abaye and רבא Rava are
more or less contemporaries and colleagues. So אביי Abaye. was giving שיעור
shiur and he said this. And רבא Rava said, אמר להון שפיר
אמר נחמני. amar lehon, shapir amar Nachmani. נחמני Nachmani said it well.
נחמני Nachmani and is the same as אביי. Abaye The question is
what was his real name? Was his real name נחמני Nachmani and
they called him אביי Abaye as a nickname? Or is his real
name אביי Abaye and they called him נחמני Nachmani as a nickname?
Yes.
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava are agreeing on something.
אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, I'm sure agreed about many, many things.
They disagree about quite a few things as well.
But, you know, so here, so רבא Rava thinks, you know, perhaps
רבא Rava even had his own explanation and then he heard אביי'ס
Abaye's was amazing.
So, some of the ראשונים Rishonim get into a bit of a
debate about what אביי'ס Abaye's real name was. At least in part,
one suggestion is that רבא Rava liked to call אביי Abaye נחמני
Nachmani because רבא Rava grew up in the house of רבה בר
נחמני. Rabbah bar Nachmani. So רבה'ס, Rabbah's, רבא'ס, Rava's, sorry, רבא'ס Rava's
grandfather, step-grandfather almost or or adopted grandfather was named נחמני. Nachmani. So
he didn't want to show disrespect to his relative by, sorry, he
wanted to show respect to אביי Abaye by referring to him in
such a way that he referred back to his adoptive family. So
he called as a nickname he, or that's one possibility. The alternative
possibility is his real name is נחמני Nachmani and אביי Abaye, is
to say
like אביי, Abaye אבא, Abba, that he's like Papa, you know like,
I don't know, people come up with nicknames. Why, like פפי בר
נחמני, Papi bar Nachmani, right?
They call him Papi.
Papi, something, right. There are all these different nicknames. You know why
was, you know רב Rav, is called רב, but רב'ס Rav's real
name was אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, the tall, tall אבא. Abba. So
how come, you know, there's a סוגיא sugia from what? From one
of the Babas that one of the, one of the אמוראים Amoraim
comes from from
בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or one of the, one
way or the other, and now I'm forgetting the whole סוגיא. sugia.
But the story is that he's sitting in the שיעור shiur and
they ask, oh so he, right, he went to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and they ask him, oh so who teaches שיעור shiur in,
in בבל? Bavel? He says oh it's, it's אבא אריכא. Abba Aricha.
They say אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, oh my god, you know, I
used to sit eight rows behind אבא אריכא Abba Aricha and he
was, you know, throwing arguments with, with רבי and they were sitting
in the שיעור shiur and it was, you know like you call
him אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, like you just, you're just call him
like by his name?
יהושע Yehoshua also is a nickname.
אריכא Aricha is also a nickname and we have you know some
strange ones, we have יהושע בן קרחה. Yehoshua ben Korcha. קרחה Korcha
means bald. You know, we call יהושע Yehoshua the son of the
bald one. You know, people had nicknames. Okay, so people had nicknames.
Nicknames catch on, sometimes it becomes the name you go by professionally.
Although it's his real name, יונתן בן כירס Yonatan ben Kiras is
mentioned elsewhere.
So there you go. So he's kind of a reference back to
תנ"ך. Tanakh. So even in, and even in תנ"ך Tanakh people have
nicknames, right? Okay. So שפיר נחמני. shapir Nachmani. Okay. מאן תנא דפליג
עליה דרבי עקיבא? man tanna de'palig alei de'Rabbi Akiva? So who is
the תנא in our משנה who disagrees with רבי עקיבא? Who is
the one who says that דלועים dilluim are not included in vegetables?
So we say, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. It's
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. He דתניא: detanya: הנודר
מן הבשר אסור בכל מיני בשר. hanoder min habasar, assur be'kol minei
basar. Because we have a ברייתא baraita that says: if a person
takes a נדר neder not to eat meat, he is prohibited to
eat all types of meat. אסור בכל מיני בשר, assur be'kol minei
basar, all types of meat. ואסור בראש, ve'assur be'rosh, it is prohibited
to eat the head, head cheese perhaps, the different meats from the
head of the animal. וברגלים, u'be'raglayim, and the legs.
ובקנה ובכבד. u'be'kaneh u'be'kaved. ובקנה u'be'kaneh is the trachea. ובכבד, u'be'kaved, and
the liver. ובלב, u'be'lev, the heart. ובעופות, u'be'ofot, and poultry.
ומותר בבשר דגים וחגבים. u'mutar be'basar dagim va'chagavim. And it is permitted
to eat fish and locusts.
That last line is the גמרא חולין, Gemara Chullin, is a משנה
in חולין. Chullin.
Right, so the last line is referencing back to the משנה in
חולין Chullin that says that בפרק כל הבשר, be'perek kol habasar, the
discussion of meat, which things, which meats are prohibited with milk. So
meat and obviously offal and poultry are prohibited with milk, but fish
and locusts are not. So this is almost to a certain extent
an extension, this actually coming from חולין Chullin and the discussion of
the נדרים nedarim, from חולין Chullin comes back here, it's interesting to
think about why the question of taking a נדר neder against eating
meat referenced in חולין Chullin and not in נדרים, but that's what
we're talking about. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הנודר מן הבשר
אסור בכל מיני בשר ומותר בראש וברגלים ובקנה ובכבד ובלב ובעופות ואין
צריך לומר בשר דגים וחגבים. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer: hanoder min
habasar, assur be'kol minei basar, u'mutar be'rosh u'be'raglayim u'be'kaneh u'be'kaved u'be'lev u'be'ofot,
ve'ein tzarich lomar basar dagim va'chagavim. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says if you take a נדר neder that meat
should be אסור assur to my mouth, that that would only apply
to meat, meat, beef, beef and lamb, but, but not to offal
and not to poultry. And obviously, so he says he's more specific.
Because people don't think of it as like meat quote-unquote, and not
פליישיג. fleishig.
So it sounds like here, again, according to this סוגיא, sugia, in
contrast to the previous עמוד, amud, it sounds like רבי עקיבא and
רבי שמעון... Rabbi Shimon... שליח going out to search for the thing
and coming back and checking. It's just, does this fall into the
category or not? So here it sounds like beef. So meat is
red meat.
You say the word בשר, basar, do you mean beef or do
you mean פליישיגס? fleishigs? פליישיגס? fleishigs? That seems to be another way
of framing the מחלוקת. machloket. Exactly. Because if I want beef and
you bring sweetbreads,
wait one second, we're going to see we have some harsh harsh
words for people who eat offal. So we'll see in a second.
Okay, ובין שאר לומר בשר דגים וחגבים, uvein shear lomar basar dagim
vechagavim, וכן היה רבי שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, vechen haya Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel would say regularly, קרביים לאו
בשר. keravim lav basar. The organs are not
meat. ואוכליהם לאו בר אינש. veochleihem lav bar inish. And people who
eat them are not civilized human beings, are not human beings. Because
it's gross. Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel again is coming
from a richer family. In many societies where people are poorer, people
will eat any kind of meat that they can get a hand
on, organ meats and different strange cuts and from different parts of
the animal. And that this is just sort of almost to a
certain sense his
socio-economic privilege and different thing like that. So it's something to think
about. אוכליהם כבשר. ochleihem kevasar.
My mother loves organ meats because when she was growing up,
right,
that's what they had.
Right, they had to eat, you know, liver and heart and and
different things. I remember there was one time I
was in Jerusalem, מעורב ירושלמי.
me'urav Yerushalmi. It was
in, yeah,
you know, lung and different things. So, okay. Okay, so Rabbi Shimon
says קרביים לאו בשר ואוכליהם לאו בר אינש. keravim lav basar veochleihem
lav bar inish. אוכליהם כבשר לעניין זביני. ochleihem kevasar leinyan zvini. So
so the people who sort of who are eating them and they
sell them as if they're as if they're meat, right? That so
לעניין זביני לאו בר אינש. leinyan zvini lav bar inish. So so
אוכליהם כבשר, ochleihem kevasar, the people who eat them are like meat,
right? לעניין זביני leinyan zvini according to how they're sold, לאו בר
אינש. lav bar inish. מה ישנא בשר עוף? mai shna basar of?
So
what does לאו בר אינש lav bar inish mean? So לאו בר
אינש lav bar inish means it's not civilized.
No, I know, but what no, what what's this אוכליהם כבשר לעניין
זביני ochleihem kevasar leinyan zvini but then what's this לאו בר אינש?
lav bar inish? What's that going on?
So the לעניין זביני leinyan zvini question is about the שליח. If
you go to the market to buy, someone sells you, you know,
I'm going to buy meat and they sell you liver, that's
לעניין זביני.
leinyan zvini. Oh, but he's still saying that they're still לאו בר
אינש lav bar inish though.
Right, they're לאו בר אינש. lav bar inish. Right.
It's a good sale and you know, but like the definition...
Exactly. Okay, so מה ישנא בשר עוף? mai shna basar of? So
why should בשר עוף basar of be different? Meaning, why should Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel say that poultry is excluded from a נדר neder
against meat? So לתנא קמא דאסיר דעביד שליח למימרא בבשר דבשר ודגים
נמי עביד שליח דאי לא משכח בשרא מייתי להו. letanna kamma d'assir
d'avid shaliach lemeimra b'basar d'basar vedagim nami avid shaliach d'ee lo meshkach
bisra maitei lehu.
So what's the difference? Because בשר עוף basar of for sure the
שליח will go back and check and say they did not have
steak, but they did have chicken. Oh, but what do you mean?
If they don't have any kind of meat at all, and he
goes back and he says, yeah, but they did have דגים וחגבים,
dagim vechagavim, they did have fish and locusts. So he says, דבר
אי לא משכחינן בשרא אייתי דגים davar ee lo meshkachinan bisra aiti
dagim
and it'll still come back and say I didn't find meat, but
they did have fish. So shouldn't that make it אסור, assur, meaning
make the fish אסור assur as well? אמר אביי, Abaye כגון שהקיז
דם. kegon shehikiz dam.
So no, we have to discuss under what circumstances would a person
avoid eating fish? Meaning that you for sure you know that a
person is not going to want fish, or sorry, no, the difference
between poultry and fish. Meaning poultry, you
that poultry and fish, the שליח would still go back and check.
Meaning they they did not have beef, but they did have chicken,
they did not have meat, but they did have fish. The person
will still go back and check about that. Really? But that's a...
no, I'm saying, but that doesn't make sense. You go
get meat and say
oh, they had meat, but they didn't,
they didn't have meat, what
about fish? Fish?
But sometimes the word בשר could just mean flesh, for example, flesh
of fish and you have flesh of locusts and you have flesh
of cow.
No one says go get me flesh.
No, but I'm trans... no, because it's the language of the גמרא.
Gemara. Now other words, if you translate it into English, we have
a variety of different terms that clarify the ambiguity that as I
understand it the גמרא Gemara is trying to figure out. What was
the guy's meaning when he used this word? We in English have
all these different terms that clarify.
I mean I guess so, because it means what?
Go get me something that's not vegetarian? You mean meat?
Well, and
the example in the תורה Torah over here, the example was he
said go get me בשר, right?
Well, the example in the תורה, Torah, the people are have a
תאוה taivah for meat and they ask משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, משה
רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu tells God, he says, מי יאכילנו בשר, mi yaachilenu
basar, he says, אם את דגי הים יאסף להם, im et degei
hayam ye'asef lahem, can they gather all of the fish? So even
fish...
He was just saying that.
He was just saying that. Well, again, there's a story in the
גמרא Gemara about a certain דרשן darshan who used that פסוק pasuk
to try to say that
fish should be פליישיק fleishig and everyone sort of laughed at him
said you don't know הלכה. halacha. But,
so again, you have to get into the question of how much
is it in the sphere of meat or not. Is it close
enough?
Right. I guess for meat sitting here, it seems kind of obvious
unless you give me meat, no one would take a bird or
fish.
Okay. So the question now is, the hanging question is, what is
the difference between poultry and fish? So meaning that since they're both
something that the שליח could go back and say, "They didn't have
meat, but they did have X," so what should be the הלכה
halacha difference because why should when you take a נדר neder not
to eat
meat, that that should include or exclude one or the other? אמר
אביי כגון שהקיז דם דלא אכיל דגי. Amar Abaye kegon sheheikiz dam
d'lo achil dagei. If a person had a bloodletting, if a person
gave blood, it's not healthy to eat fish. So you're not going
to go eat fish. However, presumably you could eat poultry.
Wait, what is אביי Abaye. trying to answer?
אביי trying to say what's the difference because we said מאי שנא
בשר עוף לתנא קמא דאסיר. mai shna basar of le-Tanna Kamma d'assir.
Right, meaning the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma against רבי שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel said when you take a נדר neder against
eating meat, it includes poultry and offal, but not fish and חגבים
chagavim and locusts. So according to the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma position,
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says poultry is included in meat. But it's
not, but fish is not. Poultry is and fish is not. But
רבי שמעון גמליאל Rabbi Shimon Gamliel says only beef, but not poultry,
and certainly not fish. So now we said מאי שנא, mai shna,
what's the difference for the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? We know that
poultry is also not beef. So when you said בשר, you also
didn't mean poultry. But it's close enough. So how come תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma thinks that poultry is close enough but fish is not
close enough? Fish is further removed than poultry. And again, that's sort
of intuitive to us.
So what about the bloodletting?
So when you go for a bloodletting, דלא אכיל דגי, d'lo achil
dagei, you don't eat fish. You don't eat fish right after having
blood.
Because a person,
meaning that the case that you're talking about is you took a
נדר neder after your bloodletting had taken a נדר neder I'm not
going to eat. Right. Something like that.
But if you didn't go bloodletting then would it be included? So
is that what he's saying?
I'm not sure. He's trying to explain what the משנה is saying.
And what the משנה is saying is that this מחלוקת machlokes highlights
the fact that after it makes sense that the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma would distinguish between poultry and fish because after a bloodletting a
person does not eat fish. Whether the נדר neder was actually taken
after a bloodletting or not becomes more complicated according to how you
understand אביי.
But it's also related to the decision that you can't have milk
and dairy with fowl, in terms of this distinction here between the
different things, fowl and fish?
Well, that would definitely be an important סוגיה sugya to analyze together
with them and to see the מחלוקת machlokes in חולין Chullin רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili even in the תנאים Tannaim there is
an opinion that the rabbinic prohibition on poultry with dairy
should
not apply and in his locale in the גליל Galil they did
eat poultry with dairy. So again, you have a question of how
much is poultry. Again, to slaughter a chicken for sure needs kosher
שחיטה. shechitah. You have to remove the blood. You have to check
for טריפות. tereifot. So in all of those ways it's very similar
to beef, but in other ways it's not. Chickens don't produce milk.
So that becomes exactly that question. And then again here, how much
is poultry a kind of meat or not? It depends which criteria
we use to determine meatiness or not.
And potentially waiting between milk and meat.
And potentially waiting as well. תוספות Tosafot in חולין Chullin there is
a discussion of the possibility that the waiting period between poultry and
dairy should be less or even no waiting period compared to with
beef that there should be a waiting period afterwards because for a
rabbinic prohibition we don't need to make a safeguard in the same
way that for a biblical prohibition.
But that's not typically practiced.
It is not typically practiced at all. I know of no one
who distinguishes.
Well, so what about ספרדים Sefardim or whatever they are? Because I
know my grandfather was saying that they wait less between poultry and
dairy and I'm not familiar with that, I'm not...
Okay, well let's keep going. So אביי כגון שהקיז דם דלא אכיל
דגי. Abaye kegon sheheikiz dam d'lo achil dagei. So it says back,
אי הכי אפילו עוף נמי לא אכיל. ihachi afilu of nami lo
achil. No, you shouldn't even eat poultry after a bloodletting.
דאמר שמואל דמסוכר ואכל בשרא
דצפרא פרח ליביה כצפרא.
d'amar Shmuel d'misukar v'achil bisra
d'tsafra parach libei k'tsafra. If a person is in such a state
and eats meat דצפרא, d'tsafra, meat in the morning, breakfast meat, פרח
ליביה כצפרא, parach libei k'tsafra, then your heart will flutter like in
the
morning, like a bird or a ציפורא tsippora like a bird. Right.
So this is that your heart will have heart palpitations. So in
other words, don't eat poultry because poultry meaning after a sensitive medical
procedure eating poultry will cause you to have heart palpitations of some
kind. מסוכר? mesukar?
Diabetic, perhaps, yeah, something like this.
No.
Okay, different ways.
Again it's not clear. שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* did have some kind of
medical training, so שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*'s medical advice, again back then the
medical training even the גאונים *Geonim* said, so it was דסכר אכלא
דבישרא דציפרא פרח ליביה דכנפי *Desakar achla devisra detzipra parach libeih dechanfi*
and ותניא *Vetania*, אין מקיזין לא על הדגים ולא על העופות *Ein
makizin lo al hadagim velo al haofot*, the ברייתא *Braita* says we
do not do a bloodletting either for fish or for
meat-meaning if you- don't eat these foods if you're going to have
a bloodletting or after a bloodletting, and he will eat בשר מליח
*Basar maliach* also salted meat, ותניא *Vetania* הקיז דם לא יאכל לא
חלב ולא גבינה ולא ביצים ולא שחליים ולא עופות ולא בשר מליח
*Hekiz dam lo yochal lo chalav velo gevinah velo beitzim velo shachalayim
velo ofot velo basar maliach*, so if you get a bloodletting do
not eat milk or cheese or eggs or שחליים
*Shachalayim*, שחליים *Shachalayim*
are- not
sure, they say cress over here. Cress.
Is that some kind of cress?
How does the קורן *Koren* translate it?
Cress is what? A vegetable of some nature.
Alizi, small leafy vegetable. Okay, I'm not sure.
Watercress and
okay, and don't eat poultry and not salted meat.
What you should eat is like fatty meat then, right?
Well, you should eat either fresh red meat and not salted, fresh
meat with the juice still in it. I mean again they had
a certain sense that you need foods that are high in iron
perhaps to replenish your blood, I'm not sure. You could make some
kind of a פשרה *Pshara* like that, but general they're saying avoid
most foods, eat bread, eat perhaps mushrooms, not much else, you know,
have a relatively limited diet after your bloodletting. Don't strain your system
too much.
There is a question whether donating blood, whether a person who donates
blood בזמן הזה *Bazman hazeh*, whether that person is halachically required to
follow the stipulations that are given
in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s medical advice. But the גמרא *Gemara*'s medical advice
in היכא דהקזת דם *Heicha dehakazat dam* may not only be medical
advice, may also be הלכות *Halachot* about הקזת דם *Hakazat dam*, certain
days that you should or should not go for הקזת דם *Hakazat
dam*, certain times of year. So as far as people who hold-
I don't know of anyone who holds by this, but I think
the question has been raised for פוסקים *Poskim*, I could look into
the question more,
but think about that.
Yeah, it's a fascinating question whether modern day- so I think one
of the answers to say it's excluded is that a modern day
blood donation is not bloodletting done as a medical procedure to improve
your own health. It's something that for some people, for certain cases
and certain people do do it medicinally for certain types of- certain
people have conditions where they have to drain their blood for certain
things, but in general if someone is going to donate blood for
someone else and also the other consideration is that you don't want
to encourage people to not donate blood. You want to encourage people
to donate blood as much as possible. Organization, blood donation, these are
all very important things that particularly that in our community we should
be involved in and it really helps the whole world that people
should have those resources available for people who need them.
Okay, and the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't try or the משנה *Mishna* doesn't
try to derive this from a פסוק *Pasuk*, it's just a typical
halachic exception.
Well, it's not here, I mean it comes up in other places
as well, it comes up in עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara* and yeah,
other places.
In other places I'm assuming it doesn't say שנאמר *Shene'emar*, right?
Presumably, presumably they are learned out as medical advice but it does
get discussed. It's all quoted in the רמב"ם *Rambam*. Yeah. I guess
the question is whether it's quoted in the רמב"ם *Rambam* in הלכות
דעות *Hilchot De'ot*, you know, most of those medical things the רמב"ם
*Rambam* puts in הלכות דעות *Hilchot De'ot*, what kind of diet you
should eat, don't eat this kind of beans in the winter, don't
eat this kind of fish in the summer, and all different- you
know, that based on the four humors and different things like that.
So we are now at the- you know, that there should be
no difference between the fish and the עוף *Of*, right? Is that
what we're saying and why- like in other words what are we
trying to do with all this?
Oh, so no, so אביי *Abaye* only gave his first answer so
far. אביי *Abaye* has a second answer coming up. So the second
answer from אביי *Abaye* we're about to hear. Okay. שאני עופות דאפשר
על ידי שליקה *Shani ofot de'efshar al yedei shelikah*. So the difference,
the difference of עופות *Ofot* is that עופות *Ofot* if you do
them שלוק *Shaluk*, you do them braised, stewed, then stewed poultry is
okay to have after bloodletting but fish is no way. Don't have
fish after bloodletting at all. And עוף *Of* you could have if
it's שלוק *Shaluk*. Okay, so that's number one. That's the difference between
עוף *Of* and דג *Dag* is that when you have a bloodletting
you could only have braised chicken but you could not have any
fish at all and therefore that's why the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*
distinguishes between fish and poultry regarding the נדר *Neder*. אביי *Abaye* now
has a second answer. אביי אמר כגון דכאיבין ליה עיניה *Abaye amar
kegon dechaivin lei eineih*. So when your eyes hurt- so again he's
saying the context of this מחלוקת *Machloket* why the תנא קמא *Tanna
Kamma* and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel* had this
מחלוקת *Machloket* and the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* included poultry in it
but not fish, meaning תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* should have included fish
but did not is because your eyes hurt. דגים קשים לעיניים dagim
kashim la'einayim? *Dagim kashim la'einayim*, fish is bad for your eyes. הכי
אכיל דגים *Hachi achil dagim*, they say the same thing do the
opposite.
Exactly. אי הכי *Ei hachi*, right?
If you're going to have an eye...
Exactly, the opposite. אכול דגים, you should eat fish because why? דאמר
שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, because שמואל learned from the letters of the alphabet
נון סמך עין, nun samech ayin, נון סמך עין, nun samech ayin,
נונא סמא לעינא. nuna sama l'eina. ההוא סוף אוכלא. hahu sof ochla.
And נונא, nuna, then it should be נונא, nuna, so it means
like fish?
So נונא, nuna,
fish, נון nun is Aramaic for fish, so נונא סמא לעינא, nuna
sama l'eina, the fish is good for your eyes.
As a סמא, sama,
a סמא, sama, a potion, a medicine for, the חיד"א Chida uses
this line in the גמרא to say that eating fish is good
to protect against, and this is I think even attested to by
earlier sources that fish, across קבלה, Kabbalah, that fish is a preventative
against עין הרע, ayin hara, that eating fish on שבת Shabbat became
a custom in a lot of communities influenced by קבלה Kabbalah for
this reason, but the חיד"א Chida also notes a custom that if
you're worried about עין הרע ayin hara to recite the 11 פסוקים
psukim in תנ"ך Tanakh that both start and end with נון nun
because of נונא סמא לעינא, nuna sama l'eina, that
the letter נון nun will protect you for your eye, which he
takes to mean the עין הרע. ayin hara. Let's do a little
bit more on נ"ה nun hey to get a little bit further
ahead so that on שבת Shabbat we won't have it.
ההוא סוף אוכלא. hahu sof ochla.
ההוא סוף אוכלא, hahu sof ochla, meaning that in the end you
eat it. Meaning that what? Meaning that נון סמך עין, nun samech
ayin, כי בסוף אוכלא, ki besof ochla, בסוף החולי, besof hacholi, because
at the end, meaning, ah no, that's a different. What is the
difference between what שואם אביי Shuam Abaye said, sorry, שמואל said, נון
סמך עין nun samech ayin that fish is good for your eyes
and, oh, but that you have an eyeache you shouldn't eat fish
because דגים קשים לעיניים? This is different stages of the illness. At
one point it's when your eyes are already in pain you should
not eat fish, but either as a preventative or once you've started
to get better, then eating fish would be helpful. Again, this is
some kind of medical advice that's not really so relevant for us
to focus on too much just because it is not well-founded in
modern medical science.
And if we choose to leave it there, then we can leave
it there and we'll pick up tomorrow. So everyone should have a
wonderful שבת Shabbat and be here between מנחה Mincha and מעריב Ma'ariv
tonight.